Hello boys and girls, ladies and germs. This is Tim Veras. Welcome to another episode of the Tim Veras Show. This is a three-way. This is a podcast featuring two Bucking Broncos and intellectual greats. I am excited to introduce you to both Wade Davis and Dr. Andrew Wilde. They've both been on separately before, but in this particular instance, they are united in their deep interest and long-term use of the divine leaf, aka coca leaf.
which has 8,000 plus years of human use documented. We'll get into lots of details on that.
and why on earth I might feature this on this podcast. But let's get to some bios for those who don't know these fellows. Wade Davis is a ethnographer, writer, photographer, and filmmaker. From 2014 to 2024, he served as professor of anthropology and BC leadership chair in cultures and ecosystems at risk at the University of British Columbia and from 2000 to 2013 as explorer in residence at the National Geographic Society.
With a PhD from Harvard in ethnobotany, he spent three years among 15 indigenous groups in the Amazon and the Andes. He's the author of 24 books and 26 languages.
We'll get to how he credits COCA for a lot of that productivity, including the Samuel Johnson Prize-winning Into the Silence. Dr. Andrew Weil is a pioneer in integrative medicine and founder of the Andrew Weil Center for Integrative Medicine at the University of Arizona, where he holds the Lovell Jones Endowed Chair and serves as clinical professor of medicine and professor of public health. He earned his biology degree from Harvard College and an MD from Harvard Medical School.
later researching medicinal and psychoactive plants at the Harvard Botanical Museum. In 1979, he founded the Beneficial Plant Research Association, revitalizing that in 2024 as its president. In New York Times best-selling author 15 books and named by Time Among the World's 100 Most Influential People, he co-founded True Food Kitchen, one of my favorites, and Macha.com. You can find Wade Davis at daviswade.com and Dr. Wilder, Dr. Wilder, W-E-I-L.
without further ado, please enjoy this wide-ranging conversation all about but not limited to coca.
I thought, Andy, we could start with the ethnobotanical medicinal side of things because I'll share perhaps an anecdote to kick us off, which was I, as both of you have spent a lot of time in South America and it's not always to end up in the lower upper Amazon consuming questionable substances. It's sometimes to do other things like visit cities and spend time with friends and go skiing. And the skiing
in this case was in Chile and it was the first instance where we landed in Santiago drove to elevation very quickly and I had my first experience with terrible altitude sickness and for those who have not experienced it I do not wish it upon my worst enemy it is an absolutely horrific experience terrible and even though
The legal status, I think, is a question mark, or maybe it's very directly verboten in Chile. The locals in the lodge gave me coca leaf tea, and within several hours, no symptoms, and they did not recur past that point, which blew my mind, particularly since even with diamox to help with altitude acclimation, my experience has been that it takes a few days.
And I did not have any good way to explain this, particularly given my levels of exertion. And not surprisingly in other countries, whether it's Peru, Colombia, certainly if you look at the Kogis and so on, this plant is not just incredibly important from a, let's just call it for lack of a better term, religious perspective, cultural perspective, but also medicinal perspective. So I was hoping, Andy, you could
give a primer on what makes coca the plant interesting. Let me say I first met coca in 1965. I just finished my first year of medical school. My mentor Dick Shultes, who was director of the Harvard Botanical Museum, sent me to South America to collect medicinal plants with one of his graduate students in the Amazon in the Andes. And I met with him right before I left, and he said, when you're in Peru, be sure to chew coca.
He said it's a very interesting plant and you want to learn about it. So I did and I have been using coca ever since. And my original interest was to find out how this was used by indigenous peoples. Medicinally, it's as important to that population as peppermint and chamomile are in European medicine. It's their major medicinal plant. And the main indication is for treating GI disorders.
But also it is obviously relied on to provide energy and doing physical work to help with altitude sickness as you mentioned to boost mood and to improve metabolism. You know the population and these especially is often not well nourished and they eat a very high starch diet. They have high incidence of genes predisposing them to type two diabetes but they don't have diabetes if they are on their traditional diets.
and exercising and chewing coca. But if they move to lower altitude and stop chewing coca and eat more like the Blanco population in Peru, they develop very high rates of type 2 diabetes. So that's quite interesting, you know, that it has some normalizing effect on blood sugar and metabolism, which is something that I'd really like to see good research on. So I think there are multiple uses and these are not attributable to effects of cocaine.
And I think this is most important that in coca, there are 14 alkaloids. Cocaine is one of them. And they all have similar chemical structures and none of them have ever been studied. You know, once we isolated cocaine from the leaf, everybody lost interest in everything else. So we don't really know what those other things do and how they modify the activity of cocaine. The amount of cocaine in coca is relatively small. Now, it would be not be worth anybody's time on a home scale to try to extract.
cocaine from coca you need tonnage of leaves to get a significant amount But I think the most important point is that this whole complex of compounds Acting together is responsible for the effects that you know people report as being you know very beneficial both for mental health and physical health Can you say more about the? Digestive or metabolic effects to we have an idea of the mechanism of action there what it's actually doing Coke has been remarkably little studied
know, for a plant of such enormous historical, cultural, economic, scientific, medical importance, there is an almost complete absence of research on it. And Wade can talk about the reasons for that. But one of the things that struck me when I was interviewing people in the Andes about the GI effects was that the respondents said that it treated both diarrhea and constipation. That doesn't make any sense from the point of view of Western pharmacology. Cocaine is a gut stimulant. So
Obviously be great for constipation, but it couldn't do anything for diarrhea except make it worse. And that always puzzled me, but then looking at these other coca alkaloids, there's something peculiar about them. If you look at the structural formula of the molecules, they resemble drugs like atropine and scopolamine, which are found in nightshade plants. And those are gut paralytics. Scopolamine has been used in medicine to treat diarrhea. So this is kind of a paradox. You've got a molecule
They're just from its shape, you predict would be a gut paralytic, but in fact cocaine is a gut stimulant. So how does this work? I think, you know, this is a model for the differences between a whole plant drug and an isolated compound. I think when you present the body with this mix of ambivalent molecules, you know, that push and they pull against physiology, the body decides what it wants to use.
That's not attributing mystical intelligence to the body. It may be which receptors are available for binding at the moment. So if there is an overactive gut motility, it selects the ones that slow that down. That's fascinating to me that Koca has this sort of paradoxical activity and lets the body can choose which action it wants. So beyond, let's just say, making bowel movement regular for lack of a better descriptor.
Is it ever used by indigenous populations for what we might consider illnesses like Crohn's disease or irritable bowel syndrome? I don't even know what the occurrence of those things would be in such populations, but is it used for other indications? It is the great remedy for all GI disorders. And also they believe that it helps them utilize the nutritional qualities of foods that they consume that often feel that if they don't follow like a meal
you know, one of their high starch meals with a chew of coca that they don't metabolize it well. There has been almost no research on this, but there was one really interesting study done with Andean Indians having them ride exercise bikes and measuring blood sugar at intervals, you know, after they gave them a glucose load. And at any point in the cycle where they began to choco blood sugar would normalize.
So this is just one study that was done some time ago. And I mean, gosh, that should just call out for a whole lot more work of that kind. That's fascinating. Yeah, super fascinating. So I wanted to just mention a few things for folks pulling from what you just said. So you mentioned Dick Schultes. If people don't recognize the name Richard Evan Schultes, I guess that's what, S-C-H-U-L-T-E-S. Look him up. Do yourself a favor and look up Richard Evan Schultes.
the bio on Richard. And with his graduate student, I worked with him as an undergraduate, but that's how way nice first met through him. Just incredible. And I may come back to the peppermint chamomile sidebar that you had because that seems interesting in and of itself. But to your point of isolated components of a plant versus the whole plant, there are many historical examples of this, one that we could pull from the head.
can show perhaps the pitfalls of isolation, not to say there aren't applications of isolation. It's better to take something like aspirin than white willow bark perhaps. But if scientists came to the premature conclusion that, well, if consuming foods with beta-carotene seems to be supportive to vision, why don't we just mainline isolated beta-carotene? Turns out not to be a great idea. There's a lot more research needed. Wade, do you want to speak to your first introduction and counter with
Coca and perhaps speak to why rehabilitation is even needed. I think some people might jump to the conclusions like well cocaine drug trade period end of story, but I suspect there's probably more there. Well, you know the thing is Tim I mean coke has been used in South America by virtually every culture of the Andean and Northwest Amazon for 8,000 years and during that time there's been no evidence whatsoever of any toxicity let alone addiction.
My first encounter was actually with Tim Plowman, who had a good friend of Andy's who introduced me to Andy, who had a great grant from Thruscheltys to study coke in the 1970s. And it spoke to the fact what Andy said is how little was known about the plant. I mean, one of the most astonishing things is that the plant had been demonized in the 1920s and yet no one had ever bothered to do a nutritional study until Tim and Jim Duke did that.
and published in 1975. And Andy was sort of on part of that team and the results were extraordinary. Not only did it have a modest amount of the alkaloid absorbed benignly in the mucous membrane of the mouth, but it was chock-full of vitamins and proteins, more calcium than any other plant studied. As Andy alluded to it, enzymes that perhaps enhance the ability of the body to digest carbohydrate at high elevation. This was food and medicine utterly benign.
The question comes why didn't someone do a study? And they didn't do a study because they didn't want to know. And I think the single most disturbing fact about coca is that the efforts to eradicate the fields, the traditional fields of coca, began 60 years before there was a cocaine problem. It had nothing to do with the pharmacology of cocaine hydrochloride and everything to do with the cultural identity of the indigenous people who revered the plant.
And what happened is physicians in Lima in particular looked up into the Andes and they saw social pathologies of literacy, poor nutrition, poverty. And because issues of economics and land reform and real economic justice challenged the foundation of their bourgeois lives in Lima, they had to find a culprit and they settled on coca.
Long time listeners know how important privacy is to me. In fact, my friends would call me paranoid or they used to call me paranoid and now they think I was just oppression in a sense. These days you may have noticed it is a lot harder to protect privacy. Anyone can find your information with a quick search. It's shockingly easy and I've had friends and paid people to read to me to try to find my info and
What you'll notice is that shadowy data brokers quietly collect and trade your home address, phone, family members, and more. It's a mess. You have to have a plan for defense, and you can fight back with incognito.
INCOGNI. Incognito automatically removes your information across 420 plus data brokers with 1,000 plus additional sites covered in their unlimited plan and they keep it scrubbed automatically. Deloitte has independently verified the headline numbers, in other words 245 million plus removal requests and the company adheres to strict security standards with an A plus rating from the Better Business Bureau. And with their unlimited plan
If you find your info on a site they don't monitor, send them a link and their privacy team will handle it. Go to incogni.com. Tim and use code TIM at checkout to get 60% off of an annual plan. One more time incogni.com. Tim, I've been eating Maui New Evanison now for more than five years and I eat it practically every week. Why on earth would I do that? Well,
It is the cleanest and most nutrient dense red meat. You can buy full stop period and even my blood work reflects this. Compared to grass-fed beef for instance it has eight times more omega-3 DHA and EPA.
four times more antioxidants and 50% more protein per calorie. Maui Nui has just released its most important innovation to date, the Ohana Reserve Aged Cuts. What is this? It is the only wild harvested Axis deer that's been naturally aged for 14 days to enhance tenderness, consistency, and depth of flavor. Reserve Aged Cuts are only available by subscription through the Ohana Reserve box.
Try it out. Visit MauiNuiVenison.com slash Tim. That's M-A-U-I, like Maui, the island, Nui, N-U-I, which is big Maui by the way. MauiNuiVenison, M-A-U-I, N-U-I, venison.com slash Tim. My observation is that Peru is actually a country with two nations within it. There is the white European nation with its capital, Lima, that has alcohol as its preferred.
psychoactive drug and there's the indigenous population mostly living at high altitude and some of the Amazon that rely on coca and those two cultures have been at war with each other ever since. For the Europeans, coca chewing became a symbol of indigenous culture and everything they didn't like and what they would love to see is either eradicate that culture or have it turn into the same as them.
Well, I mean these efforts were really pernicious and based on pseudoscience and during all those years including a famous commission dispatched in late 1940s by the UN to study this we call COCA problem that commission led by a man called Howard Fonda who's a pharmaceutical executive announced its conclusions before leaving New York and upon arrival in Lima reiterated word for word those same conclusions that the plant had be eradicated
And they spent three months in the southern Andes, meeting with military officials, Alcalde's, government officials, priests. They didn't interview a single traditional user of the leaf, and naturally, they concluded that this plant had to be eradicated. And I think if you really look at the language that you used, it was not just dark, it was racist. And that alludes to what Andes saying that
Until recently, Latin America not just Peru was very much a place of conqueror and conquered. And coca became the symbol of everything indigenous and therefore shameful for these elites. Wade, do you want to say something about the recent WHO study, which is a continuation of all this? This condemnation of coca was in language that was just so dark and racist. And the amazing thing though is that these very people with their pseudoscientific studies and their
a hideous approach in language were the very ones who wrote the language of the regulations and conventions that dictate international drug policies to this day, including the 1961 UN Declaration on Narcotic Drugs. And in all of this time, there had been no effort to actually identify the real value of the plant. And efforts have been underway more recently to get COCA descheduled or rescheduled in the UN system.
Coca leaf is now scheduled alongside with fentanyl and heroin as among the most dangerous drugs in the world. And the efforts that we've been trying to do is to get it to either be scheduled to the point where it's seen to be of problems, but medicinal potential, or better yet, descheduled altogether so that we can create a licit market for the plant. And here's the reason for that.
We have 250,000 families in Columbia that grow cocoa to survive. We need to give them a licit outlet for their product. Columbia as a nation needs the revenue, the tax revenue that comes from the international commercialization of the leaf to pay for the cost of peace, having drained its treasury for 60 years to pay the cost of a war that would have not lasted a day without the soren profits of prohibition. And above all, the world's population has a right to benefit from this plant.
You know, we have an enormous substance abuse problem in our country and a lot of it has to do with stimulant abuse. And there's also the problem of the reckless prescribing of stimulants to kids. Andy, could I ask you to bookmark that for a second? Because I want to give people a window into coca leaf so they understand the subjective experience for a second in Peru and other places. I mean, shocking to me, I think it was in Peru where I saw they were selling boxes of
coca leaf tea and the international departures wing. And I was like, guys, I want to take this with me, but I can't. The subjective effect of drinking coca leaf tea is a, among other things, a stimulant effect that is far less for me than a half a cup of coffee. But without the subsequent crash that may be due to any number of things, I think it could be a glucose spike and then sort of subsequent crash, but.
It is very, very, very mild. Okay, now we have to say that coca leaf tea is not the most efficient way to use coca. No, it isn't. The traditional way is to hold leaves in your mouth and moisten them, add an alkali which promotes absorption of the alkaloids and let it slowly diffuse into the bloodstream. Now, I don't think people up here are going to chew a mouthful of leaves, but, you know, I've always thought we could make a lozange or a chewing gum that would reproduce by the facts. Well, you could have a snooze packet like nicotine.
Right. Exactly. But the stimulant effect is so much milder, and Wade can talk to this too, I think than coffee, for example, or than any of the pharmaceutical stimulants. The really fascinating literature is in the late 19th century when physicians traveling in Peru were aware of the hazards of cocaine, but not yet judging the leaves reflexively. And their reports have this ingenuous quality, Tim, like,
I mean, there's one from the head of the British Medical Association who was 78 years old. He got up in the morning, walked halfway across Scotland, climbs the mountain, gets down, doesn't eat all day. He says, well, that was quite a day. In other words, there's this Mortimer toss it like the stimulant that's not a stimulant. And so this is really the way the plant operates, the subtlety of it. You don't feel you're stimulated. You just recognize the results of having been able to focus, concentrate, and remain at task in a creative way.
through a long period of time. But we did a little thought experiment. If I told you there was a plant that you could take that gave you a slight lightness of being, that slight kind of skip in your step, a sense of well-being that eliminated all the sort of existential little neuroses that we all suffer as conscious beings, and it allowed you to focus at task whatever that creative task was, whether it was a spinning of wool or the writing of digital code. And you could sit at task all day long
concentrating on task with immense focus, with no sense of being under the influence of any plan. Nothing is harsh as a second cup of coffee. And you found yourself at the end of the day ready to go home, have dinner and do it all over again the next day. The truth is that Coca has this capacity to improve our lives. It also helps with weight management, Tim, because it makes you less hungry and feeling like you want to move. So
That is a very desirable thing that many people would find useful and i think the mood elevating effects of coca are very significant. Let me ask a question on the mind of a lot of listeners also just add in i have used the sort of mouth buckle in the form of goes by million different names in a bomb there whatever and. Even in that case very very mild and what i would say if i were to compare it to other things.
as my long-term listeners might imagine. I've tried Medaphino, I've tried the various amphetamines, you know, Adderall, Ritalin, etc. And the difference is that, number one, you have thousands of years of human use documented in the case of COCA. Secondly, I did not seem to develop any type. I'm sure you do develop some tolerance. But for instance, if I use Medaphino for two or three days and I stop,
I immediately feel a physical requirement to use it to get back to my prior baseline and that does not happen in the case of Coca it certainly happens in the case of caffeine for me and cocaine and cocaine right but the question I want to ask is you know Wade you mentioned this enormous number of families dependent on growing Coca on an individual level I can see how hey if you ship me.
a small box of coca leaf for my personal use, there's no way I'm going to convert that into cocaine. But how do you, on a national level, if these farms are pre-existing, decouple the good of licit coca while simultaneously constraining the evils of cocaine production? Is that possible? Well, I mean, the thing there is that the status of coca has no relevance whatsoever to the cartels with
Coca is a prohibited substance they've made fortunes shipping cocaine by the ton for 50 years in the United States. And where Coca leaves to be legal with the illicit commercial export market, you would still maintain the same controls over the illicit production of cocaine that you have today. So it's kind of irrelevant. The critical thing is that crop substitution programs are an illusion because how do you transport to market
cacao or bananas when you can take cocoa paste and put it in your mochila and walk down the trail. And so this expansion of cocoa production is going on dramatically and it's having huge impacts on tropical rainforests, the deforestation since the peace agreement in Columbia is very disturbing. And yet we have millions of acres of already cut over land that we could cultivate cocoa on for the well-being of the people. And you know, I think it's...
worth just thinking about the history of this plant 8,000 years. One of the most amazing things about Coca is that it's been domesticated not once, not twice, but three separate times in human history that is unheard of. And Tim, I think one approach to the problem you brought up is education, which I'm a great believer in. I think if people knew what Coca was and understood its benefits, they would demand that they'd want it.
And that includes even people who use cocaine. I have known a number of people who got strung out on cocaine and I experienced a lot of negative effects from it. And when they tried coca and used it properly, they saw that it was a much more desirable state and they didn't want to use cocaine anymore. So I think that's something we could do. By the way, it should also mention that through an accident of history, coca is in Schedule 2 of the controlled substances act, not Schedule 1.
cannabis and psychedelics it got there and schedule two is a substances that have a high potential for abuse but have recognized therapeutic application it's only there because cocaine has limited uses as a medical drug enough to mohology and dentistry but that makes it a little easier you know leverage coke out of that controlled substance box it's just a matter of demonstrating that there are therapeutic applications that the FDA could approve.
All right, so I want to fill in a gap and then come back to problem solving. But before we get to the problem solving and policy work, I'll plant a seed, which is if these farmers suddenly could legally ship product for export or domestic use in the form of coca, could they actually get around the cartel or would they be putting a bullseye on their forehead? That's a question not for now, but for later. What I'd like to talk about first,
is the indigenous cultural context in which coca is used and its importance, right? Because as you mentioned, I mean, it's not exactly ubiquitous in South America, but in a handful of countries, I mean, coca is considered, for lack of a better term, a master plant and a sacred plant. First of all, there are four different varieties that Tim Plumman identified of cultivated coca. And
two species, each with two different varieties. And we now know that from DNA analysis that the progenitor of all four varieties was a wild coca-coconut, erythrox from grasselipis, that grows along the eastern flanks of the Andes, the Seja de la Montaña, all the way from Venezuela down to Bolivia. And what this means is that at three times in pre-Columbian history, human beings came upon this delicate little
shrub in the forest with all fruit, the color and the size of rubies and beautiful little white flowers and delicate foliage and said, ha, that's the one. And it was domesticated three times in the Montagna of Columbia, in the Jungas of La Paz in Bolivia and Peru and in the Northwest of Amazon. And that is extremely rare in the history of plant domestication. And
Not only was it domesticated three times, everywhere it was domesticated, it was deemed to be the plant of all plants, the sacred plant. And that was its status through all of at least 8,000 years and remains its status amongst those who use the plant today. Today, you know, if you watch indigenous people using coca, very often they make what's called a quinta, which is an offering.
They take three perfect leaves and put them together in a fan shape and blow on them and will whisper prayers to them. And this is very common. Well, it's more than that, Andy. When people meet on the trail, they make a cruceta of leaves and then they lift it to the highest sacred mountain, blow it. Wait, what is a cruceta? Just to provide context for people? A little cross of three leaves, three perfect leaves, and you first of all, you point it to the mountain and then you blow the energy of the leaf to the mountain.
And the metaphor is the energy leaf, like in the same way to cloud condenses to bring rain and fertility to soil. So too, this is creating your sort of connection to landscape. And every single thing that happens in the Andes, a field is planted, coca is sprinkled, tools are brought back in the evening, coca is given to them. Coca appears as a symbol of the social contract and the social nexus of people.
This is why it's so important, as the anthropologist Catherine Allen said, is that to deny people coca in the Andes is not like denying the Germans beer or the British tea or the French coffee. It's actually an act of cultural genocide because you cannot be runacuna. You cannot be of the Andes, a pachamama, if you do not use the leaves and you must use them properly. And nothing causes more offense than tourists who stuff their leaves.
as the people say like horses eating hay. And in the Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta, where the highest consumption of coca in the world, men are constantly chewing hayo. What is hayo? Hayo is the name of coca in Colombia. That is, arithroc from an overgrana-tensi, a variety of overgrana-tensi, which is a coca of Colombia and the coca used today by the mommos of the Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta.
But they contemplate the day to come, they contemplate the day that they've lived. You begin to chew leaves when you are of an age to marry. And so the chewing of leaves is the expression of the essence of who you are as a people. And that happens to be a culture that believes that their prayers literally maintain the cosmic balance of the world. And so in all of these societies, the act of chewing coca is an act of being alive and to be denied the use of coca,
is to suffer a kind of existential eradication that is complete. Now, to be fair, indigenous people throughout the Americas have the right to use coca and most jurisdictions. But of course, the cost of coca is skyrocketed with the illicit market. And so there are many communities where the tradition of using coca is being lost simply because of the price of the leaves. But again, the issue for us, I think, in our initiative
is not just a traditional use of leaf, but the right of all peoples in all places in the world to benefit from the incredible gift that this plant represents. It's Latin America's greatest gift to the world and it's one that's been denied in a way that's been incredibly unproductive. I guess potatoes are a pretty good gift too, right? So let me come back, I promised to do a call back to the question that I had bookmarked.
Doing homework for this in conversation with you guys, also lots of text messages and so on. I mean, it seems like there are many reasons that if one could wave a magic wand to create a licit trade of coca, it would be a good idea. You would have dramatic impact on indigenous land rights. You would curtail deforestation because things wouldn't be pushed to the outer edges where they can be better hidden. Certainly the sustenance and viability of these communities who are already operating.
farms not to mention the potential global impact if this were to be more widely available, certainly pending or parallel with lots more research. There's a lot of good that could come of it. Could these farms be converted to legal trade without these farmers having a bullseye painted on their head by cartel who are dependent on them for producing their product?
It's not as if the cartels are going to roll over and say, oh, go great, sell your tea to Andy Weil, Inc. On the other hand, the point is that the cartels are already out of control in Colombia and doing whatever they want anyway. And they will continue to grow coca as they want to grow coca and continue to produce enormous quantities of illicit cocaine. Whether or not individuals will be free to grow coca with impunity, obviously there's going to be consequences if the state hasn't
national interest in the cultivation, illicit cultivation of coca, will have an interest in protecting those who are growing the coca. It's not going to be some kind of smooth transition, but the point is the situation in Columbia, for example, is already completely chaotic. The production having skyrocketed since the peace agreement and parts of the country now being inaccessible, and that's really a failure of leadership by the federal state.
I don't think that's a reason not to move forward with creating illicit product for the farm families who have been waiting for this. Andy, maybe you could speak to this next just to rotate here. What is the wedge in the door? This would be a big long-term undertaking to rehabilitate COCA. So what are sort of tangible next steps you think would move the needle in a positive direction? Is it funding research? Is it...
pilot programs of some type for legal products. What do you think? I think it's got to be multi-pronged. One is creating consumer demand for creating a market in North America for COCA. If people want, if consumers want it, that will move the needle quite a bit. Secondly, there have to be FDA-recognized approved uses of it, which they're now or not. And that has to be demonstrated, that's to be supported by research.
Some obvious ones are for the treatment of GI disorders or treatment of substance abuse disorders. I think possibly for treatment of ADHD, for example, with a much safer stimulant, I think the metabolic indications that there's great potential there that needs some research to demonstrate that. But if this shows potential for preventing or treating type 2 diabetes, that would be enormous. And I think we can make a list of these things.
I think it's got to work on all these fronts. But to me, the first thing is making people aware of what coca is. You know, once you don't know anything about it, and if they do, they just think of it as the source of cocaine. So that's where we're starting. There was a big effort and a very hopeful effort to get the UN to reschedule coca. And this was done at the request of both the living and the Clemian governments. And the hope, as I mentioned, was that
Coco would be taken out of schedule, and he mentioned as Coco is in schedule two in the United States, but by the international statutes of the UN is still schedule one. And the goal was to try to get it completely descheduled as a benign plant that it is. The group that met in Vienna decided against that and to maintain the status quo to the disappointment of all advocates. And the rationale was a little strange. The reason that Coco remained the equivalent of fentanyl
is that cocaine could be extracted from cocoa. Well, everybody knows that. And the fact that nothing stopped the cartels extracting cocaine by the time. So it made no sense that logic. But because of that, cocoa remains scheduled. That was a big disappointment. But that effort continues. But we are seeing movement in the US with, you know, there was a movement with cannabis. There's been movement with psychedelics. A lot of this has been, I think,
promoted by veterans demanding access to these treatments for mental health conditions. But things finally have loosened up and maybe as part of that momentum we can introduce discussions of COCA and getting some movement there as well. I think it's possible. My sort of pragmatic hat is always wondering, well if we have
Many many many people listening to this podcast. They're probably policymakers There are individuals certainly who say to themselves hey, I would love to cut down on my coffee Maybe give Cocoa spin sounds mild maybe doing a few days of that would be wonderful But I don't know what then their next step is or how the demand or interest is Harnessed in a way that leads to broader change. Do you have any thoughts on getting specific stakeholders to
take any next steps chances are you have people from every possible walk listening to this you likely have scientists who are perhaps psychedelic adjacent maybe they are stimulant adjacent who are interested in courses the fundraising question but that's solvable i think i would be willing to help fund some research what else can be done. Well to the song if you say no this is an incredibly interesting plan.
with a fascinating history cultural relevance chemistry pharmacological effects and it hasn't been studied no it's just waiting there this would be a rich subject for investigation so i would think that people scientists who are curious about things of this sort medicinal plants medical botany natural products would want to take a look at this i'll just say because it's schedule two versus schedule one it makes the
presumably the process for researching it much easier and much less expensive. But I would say, Tim, to the entrepreneurs who might be listening, that the person who manages to crack this nut has the potential to make enormous wealth. Because I think the qualities of coca are such that they could very easily compete on the level that coffee is presented to the world. It's just a much, much better natural stimulant, a more effective one, a more benign one, a more useful one.
So when the dam breaks, it will be enormous. And again, you have issues of intellectual property, but this is a plant that's been used for 8,000 years by everybody. It's very difficult for anyone to claim the intellectual rights to this plant and as some good friends of mine say, and in this case, the plant itself has agency, you know, and the plant wants to be known to people.
And the other element of this is storytelling. I mean, Andy and I are in the midst of raising funds to make a film that will celebrate, in a positive sense, coca and the whole tradition. And it's a story of social justice, it's a story of spiritual illumination, it's a story of Andean prehistory, incredible story of cultural celebration, ethnographic richness. And I think if people embraced this story, they would be deeply moved.
And at the same time, it's also a story of incredible violation of human rights. And the egregious way by which this plant has been demonized speaks to larger issues that we face as we try to find a way to live on this planet. So I think the story is so rich. And Wade and I have been involved in an effort to rehabilitate coca for some time. In the 1970s, I started a...
not for profit foundation called the beneficial plant research association whose aim was to conduct research make people aware of lesser known medicinal plants and the main one we focused on was coca. We were way ahead of our time but we had wonderful people involved in this effort and the group laps but I revived it a couple of years ago and it's now very robust we have some really great scientists behind it.
I would urge listeners to check our website, which is dpra.org and read about the COCA project and what we are involved with. Bpra.org, is that right? Yeah. If people were interested in potentially supporting the film, is that where they should go to contact folks? Yes. Okay. All right. So that's one that people can latch on to. Now, Wade, you were delivering a summons, a call to action to entrepreneurs. As luck would have it,
We may have an entrepreneur in our midst known for true food kitchen. Not only Machikari. So Andrew, if you were going to market and you're like, you know what, let me pave the way. I'm not saying that's your plan. But if you decided I want to be the first to introduce. Cocoa, Cocoa curry. You could come up with some sure that you could do a live extension. Fantastic matcha for people who are interested. By the way, matcha and cocoa are both green powders. So I'm an advocate of green powders and.
You know, Matcha has just, this is another one that I got interested in way before its time. And I tried for a number of years to introduce it here unsuccessfully. And now it has become, I mean, it is just unbelievable. The worldwide demand for it has completely stressed Japan's capacity to produce it. So, you know, that took maybe 15, 20 years for me to get that going. Coke is probably going to take a little longer, but I am determined. All right. So what would be the levers?
or perhaps dominoes is a better metaphor that you would want to tip over on the path to introducing coca as a commercial product. Even just one good study clearly demonstrating one of these effects that we've talked about of helping people get off a much more dangerous stimulants or regulating carbohydrate metabolism, helping to prevent type 2 diabetes. Wade, what do you think? Focus seen on it.
and what Andy and I know from our personal experiences is how fantastic Coke is, how it works. I think all of us, Tim, as conscious human beings, suffer from these kind of afflictions that the Buddhists talk about, you know, this little monkey mind, this sort of little
moments of neuroses or even depression. Oh, you're lucky. Moments. Thank God. I would pay to have moments. And you know, I know I'll say something very personal. I mean, I have two daughters and they have both of them for different reasons have been on some of these serotonin uptake inhibitors, you know, Prozac and never Ritalin. But you know, I've watched that and what I experienced in my life, which is a very productive life is that I
Function perfectly well without coke. It's just like old Schulte's used to say he chewed coke every day in the Amazon He didn't shoot in Boston. I find that if I run out of coke my life goes on It's just not as nice a life and it's not as productive a life But what I find is that I'm as susceptible as anybody to mood swings to Excessing to spare whatever we call it. I think this part of the human condition it's it and see me the death is the price we pay for the glory of being alive I think
Some of these little mental fuck-ups are what we pay for for the price of being conscious. Ticket of entry, yeah. And that's the whole thing about coca is that it takes care of that. Without having any sense that you've been drugged or even stimulated, you just find that stuff flitting your way. And it just makes for a more productive life. I've written 24 books, Tim, and I made 50 films. And people, oh, he's so productive. And I just smile like the Sheshir cat. Of course I am. And Addy knows exactly how and why.
I think probably, Annie, I both share a certain frustration that you can't talk people into this show, don't tell. And it's so subtle. I remember the first time I ever really got behind Coke. It was in Panama above Cibondoy in Colombia. And Tim and I had gotten a bunch of leaves in Sylvia. And Tim was never one to rush a situation that was itself inherently pleasant. And so he just laid back in the sun and I'd been with the mommos.
But I hadn't really discovered the plant. I mean, Andy will tell you, you have to, you create a learned experience with these plants. And suddenly I just felt like I was just where I wanted to be. And that's what Andy says. When Andy, and I've quoted him many times, first went to the Goobaeo in, it was 73, wasn't it Andy? Yes. And there's a beautiful passage in one of Andy's essays where he exposed to Mamba for the first time. Mamba, by the way, for the audience is just an Amazonian form of
Coca it becomes a green powder like matcha and you don't use it with an admixture the admixture as the ashes placed in the preparation So you end up swallowing the whole the whole thing is you absorb the nutrients and so on but anyway So Andy had been exposed to Monbe and the next day with the men they gather around this kalabash and he You know he walks away as I walked away in the Northwest Amazon with a spring to your feet oblivious to the humidity
As Andy said in that wonderful passage, swinging my machete and feeling that I was just where I wanted to be. And I think that's a really great summation of the subjective effects of cocoa. And can I say, I attribute at least some of my well-being to regular use of cocoa. By the way, today is my birthday and I'm 84 and I feel pretty good.
Yeah, you look great. Yeah, people always comment on how good I look and so forth. And I have to say, Coca has contributed to that. All right. I have many more questions, but I'll try to contain, I could probably use some more Coca to get this ADHD OCD and under control. But are there for people who have heard and maybe latched onto something you said earlier, which is one good scientific study, right? I'm a firm believer in this because I've
been very active on trying to establish firsts, pilots that might be a proof of concept that then catalyze more research, etc. Are there any particular researchers who people could look to fund? Let me mention one who was on our board of beneficial plants, and that's Chris McCurdy, who is a medicinal pharmacologist. How do you spell the last name?
or he's University of Florida. He is the main person who's researched cratom and has a lot of federal support for his studies of cratom. And I met with him and got him interested in coca and he was determined to do a study that's now I will just tell you it has been a very torturous route for him to get leaves legally to study. But he finally just this week got his supply. I mean, you would not believe the red tape. Why is it so hard?
because this is the problem with coca, you know, that it's just all these regulations and fear about it and confusion with cocaine. Anyway, he's a very interesting person to talk to, but he has set up, he's just about to get going. He's doing animal research first, but is going to check, is using whole coca, trying to disentangle the effects of the different alkaloids. But one of his interests is looking at this possibility of regulating carbohydrate metabolism.
He's the main person at the moment that I know of who is doing research in this area and he's very good. I was wondering I looked him up while we were talking might not be a fit might be a fit but doctor peter Hendricks has done some interesting work mostly looking at Washington say mostly but perhaps best known for looking at the potential use of psilocybin combined with psychotherapy as a promising treatment for cocaine use disorder so there might be room for looking at as strange as it might sound to people.
Coca for cocaine use disorder that might be too hard to sell I proposed not an article that I wrote long ago saying that this would be one of the possible uses to wean people off of cocaine onto coca that would be a big step up You know I had not even thought about and I feel foolish realized that even if it's schedule to if you are say using methylphenidate aka riddle in or something else
you just synthesize the damn stuff. Whereas if you have to get actual organic cocoa leaves, that adds a whole different layer of headache in terms of procuring it, right? Because now you're dealing with importation and this, that and the other thing. Yeah, I hadn't even thought about that wrinkle. There's always a wrinkle. Okay. And for someone like Christopher McCurdy, how much do research studies like this cost?
Do you have any ballpark for folks? In my experience, it's like, okay, the number of subjects determines a lot of the cost. So if you want to power the study, if you want to try to get a properly powered study, maybe you want to increase the scope for more people to participate, et cetera. But do you have any idea? And I know you're not speaking for him, but do you have any idea what something like that might cost? More than you would think.
So, you know, that is a challenge. But you know, Chris has found that the federal government and national suits on drug abuse is willing to fund these studies. So that's very promising. Yeah. I had Nora Volkov of NIDA on the podcast a couple of years ago, and it was a really good conversation. And she was in the, I don't know if this is public, might have to scratch it, but she was in the Oval Office for the executive order related to psychedelics. And I was like, man, that's awesome.
And she's so brilliant, so I don't know what her current status is within NIDA. She might still be running it. But there seems to be a sea change afoot. So the timing could be very serendipitous to try to kick something off now, particularly on the research front. For people who might be wondering, I'll just throw out some numbers. I made early on this 2015 helping to fund some of the initial psilocybin studies looking at
depression at Hopkins. I mean, for 50k, you could make a huge, huge, huge difference. Really? That's great. It's not necessarily millions of people. It depends on, again, the size, the ambition, and you don't want to be penny wise and pound foolish, right? If you can fund more and you want to drive the possibility for a statistically meaningful outcome that is suitable for publishing and defensible, then maybe you write a bigger check.
Especially if you're gonna wait all that time because science is pretty so tell us anything about what's going on in Canada because the Regulations in Canada are a little more favorable than they are in the US and there's some research interest up there There's nothing really definitive. I mean, I think one opening in the States could be Bobby Kennedy I've been with Bobby few people know but when his father was killed was sent by the family to Columbia and he fell in love with Columbia and I've been in Columbia with Bobby with the mommos chewing cocoa
He totally understands the plant and he certainly understands the distinction between coca and the alkaloid cocaine. So I think there's an opening there which could be very promising. And one area that I very much agree with him on is his initiative to change psychiatry and move it away from the biomedical model which I think has been really failed us. I mean I think this whole coca
story you slam up against the whole failure of the war on drugs and the ideology of the war on drugs is a very. Funny account where in October in about October 2020 there's this bust at the Philadelphia International Airport of 15 pounds of what was called green cocaine and the customs agents sort of heralded this great sign of the vigilance of their colleagues and so on and.
Anyone who knew anything about anything could see that that green cocaine was Mambé. And also in the bus was a brown paste, which everybody knew would have been a tobacco paste. Now, tobacco kills 400,000 people every year, but it's legal. So this was not of concern to the agents, but the green cocaine was. And they analyzed it and discovered it had some cocaine in it.
trivial amounts so that if anyone tried to snort the mamba they just would plug their nose most unpleasantly with a powder the consistency of talcum powder. But the thing that was so disturbing about the bust is then after 60 years of war on drugs you had customs agents who still didn't know the difference between coca and cocaine after spending a trillion dollars on this failed campaign.
And that was really the equivalent, if you think about it, of Elliot Nest busting a truckload of potatoes in violation of the Volstead Act. Coca is to cocaine, what potatoes are to vodka. That's a good comparison. I like that. Or a peach. You know, we don't deny us the right to enjoy the luscious fruit of a peach because of the cardioactive glycosides found within the pit of each peach, right? Not to kind of push the metaphor, but they're truly apples and oranges.
when you combine that kind of in the moment idiocy together with the really pernicious history by which this plant has been demonized. I mean, Andy said earlier that these countries remain countries of conqueror and conqueror. And in this era where we're so sensitive to language, if people were aware of the language, and I wrote a long piece for Rolling Stone called The Secret History of Cocoa, the language being used by those who crafted the very
documents that we live by to this day is so hideous that it would cause anybody to be immediately dismissed from any position in our country today. And yet that language accusing Koki users of being Pernong, I mean, until they make this stuff up. And it was all driven by the same guy, Enslinger, who gave us Reef for Madness. And so we're still living by that mindset.
which has been utterly exposed as a racist and colonial conceit that it was. I think that coca is the most perfect example of how we've gone wrong in our relations with the natural world. Really failing to see that plant for what it is, confusing it with this one component of it, and then getting ourselves an enormous amount of trouble. In my career as a physician, I have
work for years and years to help people understand the differences between whole plants, natural products, and isolated compounds. I mean, I think isolated compounds have their place in medicine, but very often I see that these complex natural mixtures work better or much safer, often have effects that we don't have the pure compounds that work for.
Coke is a perfect example of that and Andy when you say that you know relation to the natural world in a social sense It's expressed in Peru as well. I mean one of the great Rituals I've participated in is called the mojimiento it's out of Cuzco where once each year the fastest young boy in every hamlet has given the gift of becoming a woman and he has to lead all able-bodied men on this ritual run But it's not your ordinary run you start off at eleven thousand five hundred feet run down to the base of the sacred mountain and to kill cut
9,000 feet, then you run to over 16,000 feet and you fall over two soaring Andean ridges over the course of this 24-hour race that's less a race than a ritual of ordeal. And the idea is that as you enter this race through pure exhaustion, you make the sacrifice that makes it sacred, it's from the Latin. And I did that race at the age of 48, the oldest man ever to do it and the only outsider to do it.
And I only got through that race by chewing more coke in one day than anyone in the 8,000-year history. But the point is, what Andy's saying about our relationship with the natural world, what that race is really about is expressing a sense of obligation and belonging. You're running the perimeter of the land. There's sacred mounds of earth, hikdos, muhones, where the wa'ilakama spin to bring the energy of the woman to the mount top, where coke is given to Bacchamama. And so the race becomes a ritual of belonging.
you're demonstrating your ownership, but also your obligation to preserve that land. So you see, Koka in that sense is as powerful an adjunct to culture as ayahuasca might be amongst the peoples of the Anaconda. You know, you can't do that run without Koka Tim. Koka is a mediator. You know, they often say that the first to taste the leaves was Antisima Maria in the kind of syncretic myth of origins.
When she lost the Christ child and her grief, she sampled the leaf and that gave her the spirit to continue. Well, obviously that's a syncretic fusion of Greek, Colombian and Catholic ideas, but that's an indicator of its centrality in the stream of existence and the Handys. So let me ask just a personal question of you guys, which I'm sure has occurred to a lot of listeners or…
viewers and that is like, why do you care so much about this? And it's the hierarchy of reasons like what's at the top? What is it for you, Andy? For me, it is the confusion of a plant with an element of it, which is a problem that I see in medicine greatly that we just fail to understand those differences. And I would like to help educate more people about that. And as I said, I think coca is a most perfect example of how we've gone wrong in our relationship with the plant. And also just
to, I suppose, underscore one thing, which is not what you're saying. You're not saying that all plants are therefore safe, right? That whole plants are therefore like, you don't want to go out and start chugging a bunch of hamlok tea. No, there's plenty of stuff. However, peace versus whole component versus that's a big entire plant are different. They are either way, you know, I think in our society, particularly, I think there is great fear of nature and we tend to see nature as hostile.
And many people I know think if you just go out and randomly munch plants in your backyard, you'll likely die. You know, the percentage of plants that can seriously harm you is pretty small. I mean, there aren't many hemlocks out there. There's a lot of things that might give you an upset stomach. But there's not a lot of things that can kill you or cause serious harm. I once had dinner with the chief technical advisor to one of the big European
supplement companies he was Austrian he traveled all over the world he said. One thing that struck him was the extreme fear of nature in the English speaking world i mean i never heard anyone say that but he said this is an attitude that he found very common in the UK and canada and australia and the US new zealand. He said very different to what you see for example in germans speaking europe where people tend to regard nature is friendly benign helpful you know in germany culture.
There's great use of medicinal plants in natural forms. They're very different from what we have here. So that's just an interesting perspective. I'd never noticed that. Where do you think that comes from? Any ideas? I wonder. Wait, any suggestions? I don't know. You certainly see it amongst fungalphobes, as you always talk about, Andy, the fear of mushrooms. But, Kim, back to your question. For me, I revere coca because of what it's done for my life. But also, it symbolizes for me
everything I care about in terms of cultures and anthropologists and everything I've ever fought for in terms of the rights of indigenous people and it's to me one of the most egregious violations of the rights of other cultures and it's also a denial of the genius of other cultures so it sort of symbolizes for me everything that I've stood up against in my career and it happens to be a plant that has brought benefits to me.
enormous benefits. But I'll give you, if I could share one anecdote that shows how great this all is. I don't know if you remember, but some years ago Peru qualified for the first time in 10 years for the World Cup. And I saw the victory match on a screen in Cusco was played in Lima. And then the captain of the Peruvian team who played for a squad in Sao Paulo in a random drug test was shown to have metabolites of cocaine in his urine.
and he was going to be kicked off the team. And this was going to make a huge international scandal. And his lawyer called me from Sao Paulo and I said, well, wait a minute, doesn't he come from Lima? Yeah. Well, they just went through Christmas. Didn't he go to Ayacucho or Cusco? Yeah. Oh, he must have stayed at the Monastario Hotel in Cusco because that's a nice hotel. Yeah, that's where he stayed. Well, that hotel has huge vats of coca-tea.
available at all times for its clientele for altitude sickness. And that's what he had done. He had drunk copious amounts of coca tea. And because of the idiocy of our understanding of the difference between the plant and the drug, this could have been an international incident because you well know that Peruvians like all Latin Americans take their football very seriously. But we got him off. Yeah, very seriously. Andy, it looks like you were going to say something. Do you have anything to add to that?
Nope, I think we you know we for for different reasons we come from different places We both are very passionate about this issue. Coke has always seemed to be defined as what it is not it's not cocaine and Presenting this plant in all of its glory. I mean it's interesting. You know, I mean Andy's a real plant guy He's a real ethno botanist a real physician who's always had plants in his practice And I went through a period of time where I was very much a
technical explorer, but I'm fundamentally a storyteller, a writer, an anthropologist. But this plant wrapped its arms around me when I was 19 years old and has never let me go. And I have a kind of deep fidelity. It's hard to explain. I don't normally speak in this kind of language. But this plant has given me so much and has allowed me to explore and have such extraordinary experiences in the field in pursuit of its mysteries.
and its wonder, that I feel that liberating coca is the final act of my professional life. I feel by very sincerely, and it also brings me back to Andy, because Andy was like always my big brother. Andy and Tim Plumman, who were great friends, both acolytes of sholties. And for me, I was able to come along as their kind of kid brother. So the relationship with Andy to me is enormously important emotionally, spiritually even.
And if Andy and I, in the memory of Tim, who tragically died way too young at the age of 45, the great botanical authority on coca, he died of AIDS. And incidentally, as I was reading and doing his eulogy that I conceived the book One River, which is a biography of our great professor Richard Evan Schultes, we're doing this in part in memory of Tim. I'm sure Andy would agree. We've covered a lot of ground. What I'm going to do also to try to consolidate next steps for people.
for anyone listening or watching is I'll create Tim.Blog.Coka. So on my website, that'll lead to this episode. And at the very top of the show notes, we'll have a link to the BPR.org. We'll have a link to some of the researchers who were mentioned, including any others that you guys might think of after the fact. The link to some of the pieces that Andy and I have written would be really great. We'll put a bunch of stuff at the top.
with a bias for people who are listening if they're like this is all great i don't want to be purely a passive consumer of education or edutainment like i actually want to put a dent in the world then we'll have that at the top because i don't want to bury that stuff in terms of possible next actions for people folks that'll be a tim dot blog slash coca coca just like coca cola not a coincidence by the way. Yeah i'll read you this is a piece on.
eater, people can look it up, maybe I'll link to it actually. An unassuming set of buildings in Maywood, New Jersey, less than 10 miles from Manhattan holds a surprising secret. It's what might be arguably called the cocaine capital of the United States. Here a chemical company manufactures cocaine legally with a special permission from the US government, all in service of a familiar company, Coca-Cola. Cola, by the way, just for people who like little bits of trivia, comes from Cola-K-O-L-A, well, in English at least, African nut known for its caffeine content.
And by the way, Tim, Coca-Cola notorious, we had a secret Coca plantation in Hawaii. No kidding. Scoundrels. Look at that. And you know, that is the only legal export of Coca from Peru is to that chemical company, Stephand Chemical in Maywood, New Jersey. And the cocaine is extracted and sold for pharmaceutical use.
And the rest of the leaves are made into an extract, which is a secret flavoring ingredient in Coca-Cola. And what's more, in the 1961 UN Convention on Narcotic Drugs, there was one specific exclusion of Coca solely for that company. And I got to go in Peru to where they were getting their leaves from. And they were trashy leaves. I mean, it was literally the sweepings and poor stuff that Wade and I would not chew.
Drinking sawdust. Yeah Botanical sawdust Well another bit of trivia for folks if they care 7-up used to contain lithium citrate. Oh, yes, right right back in the day Yeah, those old soda companies had some stuff figured out Well gentlemen, is there anything else before we start to wind to a close that you would like to add? Certainly I would love you guys to mention where people can find you online if you'd like them to go in any particular direction
And anything else that you would like to add, Andy? My website is drwile.com, there's a lot of health information there. And I am the founder of the Andrew Weil University of Arizona Center for Integrative Medicine. We train physicians and health professionals on that website is awcm.org. And I'm very proud of our work there. We've graduated almost 3000 physicians.
of allied health professionals from our very intensive trainings which include really good instruction on botanical medicine. I love it. And people can also find you on Instagram, etc., at Dr. Weil. And presumably you don't have a tap into the back of your brain for that. So I'm sure there's nice good publishing of valuable content coming out there so people can check that out. And then Wade? I just wanted to say, Tim, if I could just insert this in case you could use it. Is it... I've made...
a lot of reference to the egregious language by those who are responsible for the language of the UN Declaration. But maybe I could just read that the key figure was an acolyte of Enslinger, who was sort of an notorious anti-drug warrior that we almost joke about with Rayfer Madness. But this man's name was Pablo Osvaldo Wurth. He was the chief of the addiction producing drug section of the World Health Organization.
He not only conceived, he wrote the language of coca demonization in that. But listen to what he says. This is from a lecture to the Royal Society of Medicine in London on the very eve of that commission led by Fonda, going to Peru.
is apathetic, lazy, insensitive to his environment, his mind is befolged, his emotional reactions are rare and violent, he is morally and intellectually anesthetized, socially subdued, almost a slave. Moral degeneration accompanies the physical. Line is one of the outstanding characteristics, probably due to a lack of moral equilibrium. Criminality is high and barbaric forms of homicide can only be explained
by a certain moral insensibility. We are convinced that coca leaf chewing is a social evil. The chronic consumption of these leaves constitutes a social poison which undermines the physical and mental health of the population. The children of coqueros are markedly deficient in intelligence. There is no doubt that the habit of chewing coca leaves is one of the most powerful reasons for the backwardness and misery of the Indian population.
the last link in a chain of social and medical social scourges, which include, pauperism, bad housing conditions, deficient nutrition, rudimentary or completely absent education, alcoholism, tuberculosis, venereal disease and other infections and promiscuity to mention only the worst calamities and miseries. I never hurt that weight. I never hurt.
It's quite a list. This is quoted in my Rolling Stone piece, Andy. You just can't believe the language. The remedy of the moment is gradual disintoxication of the native, diminishing the production as well as the consumption of coca by means of a suitable education, by abolishing the superstition of the magic action and the well-being of the leaves, by prohibiting initiation of young, you know, goes on and on. Only with skill and patience can coca addiction be abolished.
but it can be done. Christianized Indians no longer live in the former wretched conditions and thus show themselves physically and mentally capable of freeing themselves from coca leaf chewing and addiction. And you have to think this is the man who wrote the statutes that we turn to today in the 1961 UN Convention on Narcotic Drugs. This is the language that the UN
World Health Organization has recently affirmed by refusing to reschedule or reschedule COCA. It might be time for an update. It's that bad. Can you think of any other policy that we would live by today? It's like policies have been written by, I don't know, Herman Gorein or Google's dictating religious policies today in the United States of America. And yet this is what
we are trying to deal with and confront and it is so dark and so evil. Well, it sounds like A, terrible. B, time for an update. C, I'm sure a lot of the people who are adjacently or indirectly affirming this have no idea what it actually says, right? They have not read what you just read aloud. So, worth another look, like a lot of things. And not saying it's panacea, not saying that there shouldn't be
guide rails or guard rails, but that it's worth another look. I do think the wedge in the door to pull from language earlier probably is a awareness of the benefits. And I think you guys do a pretty damn fine job of showcasing the longitudinal productivity gains of moderate sustained use and separately getting some science funded.
And I think those are parallel tracks. And the film itself being used as an educational tool to support the, I would say, both of those, the latter and the scientific exploration. Because it strikes me, I mean, look, I'm not a doctor. I don't play one on the internet, nor am I a scientist, but I like to spend time with a lot of scientists. It's like, I think about.
some of the effects of coca and the appetite suppression, but the physical vigor in the absence of food. And I wonder, man, I would love to just take blood ketone measurements of these people. Simple stuff. So simple. So, so, so straightforward. Guys, this has been wonderful. Any last closing comments, concerns, complaints? Thank you for providing a forum to talk about this. I would like to add, Andy, just one comment in which Kim just said,
and what you responded, how easy these experiments could have been done. And I think we have to remember that it's not an accident that they weren't done. In other words, the nutritional study that you and Tim did in the 1970s could have been done in the 1920s. It wasn't done because people did not want anything that would affirm the possibility that the plant was anything but the demonic entity that they claimed it to be. So it's important in all of this to remember this wasn't just sort of an accident of history.
or a casual neglect. This was a conscious attempt to demonize and eradicate a plant and not for ecological reasons, not for medical reasons, not for social reasons, for cultural and political reasons of power. Yeah. I wouldn't want to by association make policy makers feel like they need to carry the burden of what was truly a travesty if they are
in part those who's help we would like but understanding the history is important i mean will link to the rolling stone piece and also and anything else that you would like linked. For people who want to check it out attend up log slash cook i mean cook has been of incredible interest to me for decades now it is of such. Cultural importance it is of ecological importance.
economic importance if you care about conservation if you care about indigenous land rights if you care about health and performance period let's say you don't give a damn about what happens in south america but you just. Say wow i feel like pounded dog shit after three cups of coffee and then i can't sleep at night and then i'm dependent i have a headache when i try to stop it's worth digging a little deeper and educating yourself on coca may not be available tomorrow may not be available next year but.
It is deeply, deeply interesting and endlessly fascinating as a possible subject of or focus of experiments. So I will leave it at that for now. We can always and I'm sure we'll be chatting more via text. But thank you guys very much. Oh, and I would be remiss if I didn't remind you Wade that people can find you at daviswade.com. Is that right? That's my website.
That's the main place. Anywhere else you would like to point people, we got Wade Davis official on Instagram, ex-author Wade Davis. I think people would be intrigued by the Book One River, which is really a count of Tim and I and Coca and Shultes. It's a great book. That book in particular would open people's eyes. Yeah, perfect. All right. Check out One River, folks. Again, we're grateful for your support very much so and make a big difference. Yeah, thanks so much to you. My pleasure. My pleasure. Very grateful. Yeah. I love...
This is important stuff. And it's also while I have this before AI gobbles every podcast, I would like to surface subjects that are of importance that have not yet been reputationally de-risked. I don't have to report to any corporate overlord who can fire me or throttle my sponsors or whatever it might be. So I have the incredible accidental
luxury of being able to and joy of being able to have these conversations with folks like the two of you who are bringing in decades of expertise and research. So always appreciate the time. Always nice to see you both. And for people listening as always show notes, check it out. Tim dot blog slash coca. Coca will go straight to this episode and give you more information on where you can learn more.
And until next time, be just a bit kinder than is necessary to others and to yourself. Compassion. Oh yeah, that applies to yourself too. Don't forget that. And as always, thanks for tuning in. Hey guys, this is Tim again. Just one more thing before you take off. And that is Five Bullet Friday. Would you enjoy getting a short email from me every Friday that provides a little fun before the weekend?
Between one and a half and two million people subscribe to my free newsletter, my super short newsletter called Five Bullet Friday. Easy to sign up, easy to cancel. It is basically a half page that I send out every Friday to share the coolest things I've found or discovered or have started exploring over that week. It's kind of like my diary of cool things. It often includes articles I'm reading, books I'm reading,
albums, perhaps gadgets, gizmos, all sorts of tech tricks and so on that get sent to me by my friends, including a lot of podcast guests and these strange esoteric things end up in my field. And then I test them and then I share them with you. So if that sounds fun, again, it's very short, a little tiny bite of goodness before you head off for the weekend, something to think about.
If you'd like to try it out, just go to tim.blog.friday. Type that into your browser, tim.blog.friday. Drop in your email and you'll get the very next one. Thanks for listening.
I've been eating Maui Nui venison now for more than five years and I eat it practically every week. Why on earth would I do that? Well, it is the cleanest and most nutrient dense red meat. You can buy full stop period and even my blood work reflects this. Compared to grass-fed beef, for instance, it has eight times more omega-3 DHA and EPA.
four times more antioxidants and 50% more protein per calorie. Maui Nui has just released its most important innovation to date, the Ohana Reserve Aged Cuts. What is this? It is the only wild harvested access deer that's been naturally aged for 14 days to enhance tenderness, consistency, and depth of flavor. Reserve Aged Cuts are only available by subscription through the Ohana Reserve box.
Try it out. Visit MauiNuiVenison.com slash Tim. That's M-A-U-I, like Maui, the island, Nui, N-U-I, which is big Maui, by the way. MauiNuiVenison, M-A-U-I, N-U-I, venison.com slash Tim. Long time listeners know how important privacy is to me. In fact, my friends would call me paranoid, or they used to call me paranoid. And now they think I was just oppression in a sense. These days, you may have noticed, it is a lot harder
to protect privacy. Anyone can find your information with a quick search. It's shockingly easy and I've had friends and paid people to read to me to try to find my info. And what you'll notice is that shadowy data brokers quietly collect and trade your home address, phone, family members and more. It's a mess. You have to have a plan for defense and you can fight back with incognito. That's
INCOGNI. Incognito automatically removes your information across 420 plus data brokers with 1000 plus additional sites covered in their unlimited plan and they keep it scrubbed automatically. Deloitte has independently verified the headline numbers, in other words 245 million plus removal requests and the company adheres to strict security standards with an A plus rating from the Better Business Bureau and with their unlimited plan
If you find your info on a site they don't monitor, send them a link and their privacy team will handle it. Go to incogni.com slash tim, i-n-c-o-g-n-i dot com slash tim and use code TIM at checkout to get 60% off of an annual plan. One more time incogni.com slash tim.